In this video, I look into
weight loss supplements.
If you’re interested in
more on weight loss,
look no further than my
book How Not to Diet,
and of course lots of videos
if you go to NutritionFacts.org
and just type in "weight loss"
in the search bar
and you can watch to
your heart’s content.
"Are Weight Loss Supplements
Safe and Effective?"
According to a national survey,
a third of adults who’ve made
serious attempts at weight loss
have tried using dietary supplements,
for which Americans spend literally
billions of dollars every year.
Most mistakenly thought
that over-the-counter
appetite suppressants, herbal products,
and weight loss supplements
had to be approved for safety
by some governmental agency,
like the FDA, before
being sold to the public,
or at least include some
kind of warning on the label
about potential side effects.
Nearly half even thought
they had to demonstrate
some sort of effectiveness.
None of that is true.
The Food and Drug Administration
estimates that dietary supplements
in general cause 50,000
adverse events annually,
most commonly liver
and kidney damage.
Of course, prescription drugs
don’t just adversely effect,
but kill more than 100,000
Americans every year,
but at least you notionally have
the opportunity to parse out
the risks versus benefits thanks
to testing and monitoring requirements,
typically involving thousands
of individuals.
When the manufacturer of the ephedrine-
containing supplement Metabolife 356
had it tested—on just 35 people—
only minor side effects were found,
such as dry mouth,
insomnia, and headaches,
however, once unleashed on the
populace, nearly 15,000 adverse effects
were reported before it
was pulled from the market,
including heart attacks, strokes,
seizures, and deaths.
Given the lack of government
oversight, there’s no guarantee
that what’s on the
label is even in the bottle.
FDA inspectors have found 70%
of supplement manufacturers
violated so-called Good
Manufacturing Practices,
which are considered the
minimum quality standards.
This includes things like basic
sanitation and ingredient identification.
Not 7% in violation, 70%.
DNA testing of herbal
supplements across North America
found that most could
not be authenticated.
In 68 percent of the supplements
tested, the main labeled ingredient
was missing completely and
substituted for something else.
For example,“St. John’s wort”
supplement containing nothing but senna,
a laxative that can
cause anal blistering.
Only 2 out of 12 supplement
companies had products
that were accurately labeled.
This problem isn’t limited
to just fly-by-night phonies
in some dark corner of the internet.
The New York State Attorney
General commissioned DNA testing
of 78 bottles of commercial
herbal supplements sold
by Walgreens, Walmart, Target, and GNC.
Four out of five bottles didn't contain
any of the herbs on their labels.
Instead, capsules were often
little more than cheap fillers
like powdered rice “and houseplants.”
In my last video I noted that one
investigation found four of out five
bottles of commercial herbal
supplements bought at major retailers
didn’t contain any of
the herbs on their labels,
instead often containing
little more than cheap fillers
like powdered 'rice and "houseplants".'
At least you hope it
just contains houseplants.
Weight loss supplements are infamous
for being adulterated with drugs.
In a sampling of 160 weight
loss supplements that claimed
to be “100 percent natural,”
more than half were tainted
with drugs, active pharmacological
ingredients, ranging from
antidepressants like Prozac to
erectile dysfunction meds like Viagra.
Diuretic drugs are frequent
contaminants, which makes sense.
In my Keto videos, I talk
about rapid water loss
as the billion-dollar gimmick
that has sold low-carb diets
for more than a century.
But why the Viagra?
At least the spiked Viagra and
Prozac are drugs that are legal.
Researchers in Denver tested
every weight loss supplement
they could find within a 10-mile
radius and alarmingly found
a third were adulterated
with banned ingredients.
The most common illegal adulterant
of weight loss supplements
is sibutramine, which was sold as Meridia
before it was yanked off the market
back in 2010 for heart
attack and stroke risk;
now also blamed for cases of
slimming supplement-induced psychosis.
An analysis of weight loss
supplements bought off the internet
advertised with claims such as “purely
natural", "harmless", or "traditional herbal",
found that a third contained high-dose
banned sibutramine, and the
rest contained caffeine.
Wouldn’t you be able to tell if
caffeine was added to a supplement?
Perhaps not if it also had Temazepam
added, a controlled substance
(benzodiazepine) “downer”
sedative found in half
of the caffeine-tainted supplements.
Doesn’t the FDA demand recalls
of adulterated supplements?
Yeah, but they just pop right
back up on store shelves.
Twenty-seven supplements purchased at
least six months after the recalls were
released, and two-thirds still contained
banned substances—17 out of the 27—
with the same pharmaceutical
adulterant found originally,
and six containing one or more
additional banned ingredients.
Aren’t the manufacturers
penalized for noncompliance?
Yes, but “fines for violations are
small compared to the profits.”
One of the ways supplement
makers can skirt the law
is by labeling them as “not
intended for human consumption,”
for example labelling
the fatal fat-burner DNP
as an industrial or research chemical.
That’s like how designer street
drugs can be sold openly
at gas stations and convenience
stores as “bath salts.”
Another way is to claim synthetic
stimulants added to slimming
supplements are actually natural
food constituents, like listing the
designer drug dimethylamylamine
(DMAA) as “geranium oil extract.”
The FDA banned it in 2012 after
it was determined that DMAA
was “not found in geraniums.”
(And who eats geraniums anyway?)
Despite being tentatively tied to cases
of sudden death and hemorrhagic stroke,
DMAA has continued to be found
in weight loss supplements
with innocuous names like Simply
Skinny Pollen made by Bee Fit with Trish.
There is little doubt that
certain banned supplements,
like ephedra, could
help people lose weight.
“There’s only one problem,”
wrote a founding member of the
American Board of Integrative Medicine:
“This supplement may kill you.”
Are there any safe and effective
dietary supplements for weight loss?
When popular slimming
supplements were put to the test
in a randomized placebo-
controlled trial,
not a single one could
beat out sugar pills.
A systematic review of
systematic reviews of diet pills
came to a similar conclusion:
none appear to generate
appreciable impacts “on body
weight without undue risks.”
That was the conclusion
reached in a similar review out
of the Weight Management Center
at Johns Hopkins recently,
which ended with this: “It is
fitting to highlight that perhaps
the most general and safest alternative/
herbal approach to weight control
is to substitute low-[calorie] density
foods for high-[calorie] density
and processed foods, thereby
reducing total [calorie] intake.”
In other words, more whole plant
foods and fewer animal foods and junk.
“By taking advantage of
the low-[calorie] density
and health-promoting
effects of plant-based foods,
one may be able to achieve
weight loss, or at least assist
weight maintenance without
cutting down on the volume
of food consumed or
compromising its nutrient value.”